<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the armie, presented to the Kings Majesty in the Isle of Wight; declaring, their full resolution touching His Majesties Reign and government, and we ring [sic] the crown of England; and their proposals upon what terms and conditions they will re-inthrone Him. With His Majesties vow and protestation touching the army. Also, the armies propositions to the generall councel of the army at St. Albanes, concerning King, Lords, and Commons, debated on Wednesday last, Novemb. 8. 1648.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E470_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205670</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864982</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864982</idno>
            <idno type="VID">162394</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 162394)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 75:E470[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the armie, presented to the Kings Majesty in the Isle of Wight; declaring, their full resolution touching His Majesties Reign and government, and we ring [sic] the crown of England; and their proposals upon what terms and conditions they will re-inthrone Him. With His Majesties vow and protestation touching the army. Also, the armies propositions to the generall councel of the army at St. Albanes, concerning King, Lords, and Commons, debated on Wednesday last, Novemb. 8. 1648.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for C.W. neer the Royal Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On the titlepage the "a" in "wearing" has failed to print.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "nou: 9th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:162394:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE ARMIE, Preſented to the Kings Majeſty in the Iſle of <hi>Wight;</hi> Declaring, their full Reſolution touching His Majeſties Reign and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and we ring the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> and their Propoſals upon what Terms and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they will re-inthrone Him.</p>
            <p>With His Majeſties Vow and Proteſtation touching the Army.</p>
            <p>Alſo, the Armies <hi>Propoſitions</hi> to the Generall Councel of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my at St. <hi>Albanes,</hi> concerning <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> debated on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> laſt, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 8. 1648.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of King Charles I of England</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <add>nou: 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </add> 
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>C. W.</hi> neer the Royal Exchange, 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration_of_the_army">
            <pb facs="tcp:162394:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:162394:2"/>
            <head>A DECLARATION OF THE ARMIE SENT To the Kings Majeſty in the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> Declaring their Reſolution and Intentions touching the Treaty.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Maieſty,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVHereas,</hi> the Officers and Souldiery un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the immediate conduct of hi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency the Lord Generall <hi>Fairfax,</hi> are poſseſt with divers fears and jealouſies, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſafe for the future, unleſſe ſpeedy Iuſtice be exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:162394:3"/>upon the capitall Offenders of this Nation; and that this preſent Treaty may not conclude a peace with his Majeſty, without care, taken to preſerve the Liberties and Freedomes of the people of this Nation; the which, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing granted and confirmed, we do declare, that none ſhall be more inſtrumentall for the ſetling of a ſafe and well-grounded Peace, then our ſelves. And that ſo ſoon as your Majesty ſhall be pleaſed, to enact and make proviſions for the free-born people of <hi>England,</hi> that both we and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Generations may defend our ſelves againſt inſulting tyranny and oppreſſion; We ſhall uſe our utmost endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for the re-inveſting of your Royall perſon, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king You and Your Poſterity happy and glorious through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Ages.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter (or Declaration) is ſaid to be ſent from divers Officers and Souldiers in the Weſt of <hi>England,</hi> to his Majeſty; for the better expelling of the Cloud of Jealouſie, and cleering all doubts and ſcruples that may ariſe in his Majeſties Royall Breaſt; And that their actions may appear viſible to the World, of their candid Intentions, and unanimous Reſolutions for <hi>peace,</hi> and compoſing of all differences both in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> the Agents of the ſeverall Regiments have commanded theſe enſuing Propoſals to be forthwith printed and publiſhed; a Copy whereof were preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Excellency the Lord Gen. <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and the Generall Councel of the Army on <hi>Turſday</hi> laſt, which were as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <list>
                  <item>1 That execution of Iustice may bee done upon thoſe who raiſed the former and the later warres against the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> And that there not be any exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:162394:3"/>of perſons from Justice, to neither King nor Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</item>
                  <item>2 That the Treaty may not conclude a peace with the King and his party, without care taken to preſerve the Liberties and Freedomes of the people of this Nation.</item>
                  <item>3 That limits may be ſet to bind Kings for the future, that they ſhall not have power to inſlave the people by tyranny and oppreſſion, and tryumph upon them as over conquered ſlaves.</item>
                  <item>4 That proviſions be made for the people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that both we and future Generations may defend our ſelves againſt inſulting Kings.</item>
                  <item>5 That there may be ſome courſe taken for pay for the Souldiery, that have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and been faithfull to the Parliament. And ſufficient ſecurity thereunto for them, to guard them in what they have done.</item>
                  <item>6 That theſe, and ſuch other things as ſhall be agreed on by the Generall Councell, may be ſent to the Houſe of Commons by the Lord Generall, and his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency to deſire a ſpeedy anſwer therein.</item>
               </list>
            </q>
            <p>Some other Propoſals were preſented to the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell of the Army, by the Agents of the reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Regiments, Declaring, that there is now a deſigne on foot to reſcue the King from the Iſle of Wight, and therefore deſire that a ſufficient ſtrength may be ſent to guard the ſaid Iſland, and to prevent the reſorting of Malignants thither.</p>
            <p>Theſe Propoſitions were preſented on <hi>Munday</hi> laſt, and debated <hi>Tueſday</hi> and <hi>Wedneſday;</hi> and there is no doubt but a mutuall concurrence and agreement will attend the cloſe of this happy Meeting, which ſo much concerneth the good and welfare, both of <hi>Religion. King, and Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:162394:4"/>
            <head>Bloudy Newes from the Engliſh Navy.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ON Thurſday laſt being the 2. of this inſtant Novem. we received an Allarum from Sea, occaſioned by certaine ſhips, who had the Princes colours, and ſtruck ſayl within three leagues of <hi>Helverd-ſtuce;</hi> whereupon the Lord Admirall ſent forth three Frigats, and two of the great Veſſels, who chaſed them, and gave them many a gallant ſhot, and after few hours diſpute, boarded one of them, &amp; ſunk another; the Maſter of the prize which was taken, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that they were bound for the Prince, with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to joyn with him, and to aſſiſt his Highneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p>This Fleet is ſaid to conſiſt of about eleven ſhips, moſt of them being men of Warre, and it is rumour'd, that they were moſt of them Swediſh Ships.</p>
            <p>But the Princes Fleet hath declared, that they will not be commanded by any ſtrangers, who ſince the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſing of the Lord <hi>VVilloughby,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Batten,</hi> have made Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> Lord Admirall; but the Sea-men were ſo much inraged and troubled thereat, that they began to mutiny, reſiſted the Command of Pr. <hi>Rupert</hi> and the reſt of the Iriſh and Dutch Commanders, fell to blowes, killed 3 or 4 eminent Commanders, woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded divers of them, amongſt the reſt, Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> hath received a dangerous wound, and its thought mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. The Conflict being ended, the Mariners of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted ſhips called a Councell amongſt themſelves, turned out Pr. <hi>Rupert,</hi> and divers others, and have made choice of new Commanders.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:162394:4"/>
            <p> They have ſent a Letter to the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite him aboard; but by reaſon of the weakneſſe of his body, occaſioned by ſudden ſickneſſe, and a dangerous diſeaſe, He cannot anſwer their expectations.</p>
            <p>The Lord Admiral hath again offered them Indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and it is conceived they will embrace the ſame, for they have proteſted to his Lordſhip, never to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage with the Princes Cavalry.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gowry,</signed> 
               <dateline>From aboard the Fleet <date>6 Novemb. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head type="sub">An Abſtract from the King.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>FOr the better faciliating the work in hand, we hear that his <hi>Majesty</hi> hath ſent a Meſſage (by the D. of <hi>Lenox</hi>) to the Aldermen and Common-councell of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and alſo to divers members of both Houſes, intimating, <hi>That He deſired a longer time to be added to the Treaty, deſiring them to be inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall for the re-inveſting of his Maieſty, and to agitate for his ſpeedy comming to</hi> London, with other remarkable Occurrences, which He deſires may be cammunicated to his Royall hearted Citizens, and that they may ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly read and peruſe the ſame. It is conceived his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty hath ſome notable deſign againſt the Army, for He hath vowed to play a new Game, if the Treaty take not effect. But upon the cloſe of this Letter, here arrived a <hi>Poſt</hi> from the Army to Col. <hi>Hamond,</hi> deſiring him to be vigilant for the laſt 14 dayes added to the <hi>Treaty,</hi> and to prevent his <hi>Maieſties</hi> eſcape, there being a deſign laid for the conveying of his perſon away, if
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:162394:5"/>he cannot accompliſh his deſires in the ſaid reſpit of time. Col. <hi>Hamond</hi> is extraordinary vigilant in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the great truſt repoſed in Him, and hath declared <hi>that he will uſe his utmo<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t endeavours for the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of His Majeſties Royall perſon from the hands of his Enemies, and to protect him from the rage and ſubtilty of thoſe who ſeek his Maieſties ruine</hi> [meaning the Royall party now reſident at his Court] <hi>And the Souldiery doe aſsure him, they will live and die with him therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Newport <date>7 Novemb. 1648.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>Letters further from the Iſle of Wight,</hi> Novemb. <hi>8. advertize,</hi> That his Majeſty having received intelligence of the new modelling &amp; chuſing ſeverall Agents through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Army, to act in behalf of their reſpective Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and of the calling a Generall Councell; as alſo, that they were poſsest with feares and jealouſies, that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty had a deſign to eſcape from the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> if the Treaty took not effect: Therefore his Maieſty declared (in preſence of the Commiſſioners) That rather then he would stain his honour or be accounted perjur'd, in breaking of his Royall Word or Promiſe, He would finiſh His whole Race in priſon, and become the most deplorable Obiect of all Christian Princes.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
